Guide to the Records of the Public History Program RG 20.9
New York University Archives
Records of the Public History Program
1981-2007
RG 20.9
New York University Archives
17.25 linear feet
This collection contains the administrative records and semester projects of the Public History Program at New York University. Founded in 1981 by Paul H. Mattingly and Daniel J. Walkowitz, the Public History graduate program at NYU was one of the first of its kind in the nation. Until 2007, the Introduction to Public History course culminated each year in an all-day workshop that took place at the end of the Spring semester. The workshops were essentially public presentations of students' collaborative research projects focusing on different New York City neighborhoods. Many of these projects exist within this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Records of the Public History program date from the founding of the program in 1981 until 2007. The types of items that comprise the collection are paper-based records such as correspondence, annual reports, student compositions, publications, advertisements, and reference materials. The collection additionally contains a range of audio-visual records, including 35mm slides, analog video cassettes, audio cassettes, Hi-8 video cassettes, VHS cassettes, and DVDs.
A considerable amount of material within this collection may risk violation of the Family Educational Records Privacy Act (FERPA), and at a later date, will be inspected for potential removal. Folders that contain sensitive information have been marked accordingly by the processor.
The collection has been arranged into six series. All records are arranged chronologically within each series, with the exception of personal files that are arranged alphabetically by surname.
Series I: Personal Files. Contains records pertaining to specific individuals who have associated with the program. The series has been divided into two subseries: those attributed to prospective students, and those relating to individuals who became directly involved with the program.
Subseries A: Prospective Student Files. Contains correspondence, resumes, and other papers relating to individuals who were considering the program amongst their academic prospects.
Subseries B: Student and Faculty Files. Contains records that pertain to accepted students and faculty members. The majority of the files are student-related, with only a few files attributed to faculty. These records include correspondence, resumes, and published work of program alumni.
Series II: Program Files. Series is divided into two subseries: one pertaining to administrative records and one including course records.
Subseries A: Administrative Files. Contains records of the program's original directors, Paul Mattingly and Daniel Walkowitz, as well as those produced by departmental administrative assistants. These records allowed for proper functioning of the program with regard to budgeting, financial assistance, and correspondence with external institutions and individuals.
Subseries B: Course Files. Contains records on the development of the program curriculum. These records include syllabi, correspondence amongst professors and deans, and course evaluations.
Series III: Publications. Contains a collection of the program's official newsletters dating from 1984 to 2002. Records included in this series are published versions of newsletter issues, in addition to article drafts and promotional material involved in the planning process.
Series IV: Activities. This series contains records pertaining to the varied activities of the program. The majority of these records can be attributed to the Public History Workshops, and others to the Public History Forums. A small amount of records covers activities not related to either of these events. The series has been divided into three subseries to reflect the distinctions in these activties.
Subseries A: Contains records pertaining to Public History Workshops dating from 1982 to 2007. Records of these workshops include student compositions, correspondence, promotional material, and reference material.
Subseries B: Contains records from the Public History Forums dating from 1984 to 1988. Records of the forums include correspondence, promotional material, and presentation notes.
Subseries C: Contains records from various activities, including field trips, conferences, and other social events.
Series V: Reference Material. Contains educational material published by external institutions and organizations on various topics, such as: New York City, New York University, the Public History movement, and the archival profession. The subjects covered in these publications are those not specifically covered in the Public History Workshops, either entirely unrelated or more broad in scope.
Series VI: Multimedia. Contains audio and visual based materials dating from 1981 to 2007 that relate both directly and indirectly to the program. Most of these materials are related to Public History Workshops, either as recordings of the events or student work involved in their creation. Other records in this series include historical documentaries and educational radio programs. A second accession was made to the collection which contained only multimedia items, mainly VHS cassette tapes and DVD-R disks. These items are housed in Boxes 15 and 16.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are ordered into six series.
Series
Personal Files
Program Files
Publications
Activities
Reference Material
Multimedia
Historical Note
Created in 1981 by Paul H. Mattingly and Daniel J. Walkowitz, the Public History graduate program at NYU was one of the first of its kind in the nation, and has maintained such prominence through the innovative work of its students, faculty, and alumni. Drawing its inspiration and guidance from the intellectual movement of the same name, the program at NYU was founded upon a fundamental objective to connect the general public with its past. In contrast to academic historians who primarily write for an audience of peers, public historians seek to produce meaningful historic representations for a broader, more popular audience. They are employed in a wide array of environments, ranging from archives to libraries, historical societies to historic sites, and museums to national parks. The alumni of the program have taken positions at highly regarded historic institutions in New York City, including The Lower East Side Tenement Museum, The Museum of the City of New York, and The New-York Historical Society. They have also proved influential in the establishment of such non-profit organizations as City Lore and the American Social History Project. Their analyses of their public history activities have been published in national periodicals and they have proved active members of the field's professional organization, the National Council on Public History. The great contributions to the field made by alumni have allowed the program to prosper over the years and have led to the recognition it receives today.
Over the course of its existence, the Public History program curriculum has evolved to adapt to changing technologies and student needs. For its initial four years, the Public History program was simply a concentration accompanying the general history M.A., requiring three courses: Local and Community History; History and Public Policy; and Media and History. These courses became the core of the program and have been consistently offered to the present day. In 1985, student demand arose for closer ties between class readings and the practical projects they were responsible for. Consistent demand led to the creation of the Introduction to Public History course. The introductory course was designed to provide a more general view of issues that were more fully developed in the three core classes. During the 1980s, other electives emerged, considering issues such as: material culture, cultural resource management, and historical fiction.
Until 2007, the Introduction to Public History course culminated each year in an all-day workshop that took place at the end of the Spring semester. The workshops were essentially public presentations of students' collaborative research projects. A specific topic, typically a New York City community, was selected for each year's workshop, and all student research centered around this singular topic. The resulting workshop would often be held within that particular neighborhood and would include participation of local scholars and residents. Several workshops established collaborative efforts between the program and historical organizations, including The Museum of the City of New York, The Lower East Side Tenement Museum, The Bread and Roses Historical Collective, and the New York Labor History Project.
Upon his assumption of the directorial position in 2007, Peter J. Wosh made a significant structural change to the introductory course, in response to both student feedback and his own professional experience. He felt that students would be better prepared for the employment arena by becoming immersed in the field during their studies. In place of the comprehensive workshop projects, Public History students would take on intern positions in historic institutions of their choice, completing tasks that correlate with their professional interests. They would produce a final project to formally evaluate their experiences, and would attend biweekly class meetings to discuss their experiences with fellow students.
Beginning in the Fall of 2008, the M.A. program in Public History merged with the M.A. program in Archival Management (also headed by Professor Wosh), to form a dual degree program, through which students would acquire a grounding in both fields. It is commonly expected that most students will be drawn to one one field more than the other. Another recent curricular alteration occurred in response to the rapidly evolving digital field and the quest of historians to keep in tune with new technologies. A Digital Media Specialist was hired in the Fall of 2008 to help integrate digital issues into current courses, particularly the History and New Media course. In addition to the core class on History and New Media, an Advanced Digital History course has been created by Professor Wosh and this specialist, to be introduced in Fall of 2009.
In addition to coursework, the Public History students also participate in monthly mid-day conferences, often referred to in earlier years as 'Public History Forums,' and more recently as 'brown-bag lunches.' During these meetings, students, faculty, and guests gather to socialize and discuss relevant issues to the Public History arena. Typically, a panel of professionals is invited to make presentations and offer advice to current students. Recent panel topics have included employment prospects and digital media initiatives.
Series IV separated due to size differences
Due to differences in letter (8 1/2 x 11 in.) vs. legal (8 1/2 x 14 in.) sizes in Series IV, the materials in this series (particularly Public History Workshop related) have been divided amongst Boxes 3-5, and Box 14. The oversized materials are located in Box 14, a manuscript box.
Physical Access
Please note that this collection is stored offsite, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Lower East Side Tenement Museum.; Mattingly, Paul H. -- History; Museum of the City of New York.; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science.; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science.; New York University.; Seward Park High School.; Walkowitz, Daniel J. -- History; Advertisements.; Audiovisual materials.; Chelsea (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights and socialism |z United States; Correspondence.; Curriculum planning.; East Village (New York, N.Y.); Grant proposals.; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z United States; King Juan Carlos Center; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Museums and community.; New York (N.Y.); New York (State) |x History, local; Oral histories (document genres).; Public history.; Publications.; Research notes.; Social change.; Social history.; Student activities.; Union Square (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Social conditions; Washington Square Park (New York, N.Y.); Washington Square |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: Personal Files
  - Subseries A: Prospective Student Files, 1981-2002
    FERPA violation
    The contents of this subseries contain student work or personal information that may be in violation of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA).
  - Subseries B: Student and Faculty Files
    Missing files
    The original accession record for this collection lists a number of student-related files that were not present upon the beginning of its formal processing. These files may have been removed earlier due to sensitivity of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA).
    FERPA Violation
    The contents of this subseries contain personal information that may violate the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA).
- Series II: Program Files, 1981-2005
  - Subseries A: Administrative Files, 1981-2005
    - Affiliated Institutions and Organizations, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
      The contents of this folder contain personal information that may violate the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA).
      Barcode
      Barcode: 3-1142-04227300-6
    - Student and Faculty Directories, 1983-1996 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Annual Progress Report, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Budget, 1981-82, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Budget Proposal, 1982-86, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Budget, 1982-83, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Budget, 1983-84, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Budget, 1984-86, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Budget, 1986-87, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Barcode: 3-1142-04227301-4
    - Budget, 1987-88, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Budget, 1988-89, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Budget, 1989-90, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Budget, 1990-91, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Budget, 1991-92, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Budget, 1992-94, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Budget, 1995-98, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Budget, 1999-01, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Budget, 2001-04, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Budget, 2004-05, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Equipment, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Equipment, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Equipment, 1993-98, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Equipment, 2000-04, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Equipment Handbooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Computer Reports, 1983-2004 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - UC Santa Barbara Grant Proposal, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Curricular Challenge Grant, 1982-84, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - NEH Grant Guidelines, 1988-91, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Curricular Challenge Grant, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Curricular Challenge Grant, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - LINKS Grant, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - NYU Research Challenge Fund, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Curricular Challenge Grant, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Curricular Challenge Grant, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - National Council on Public History Memoranda, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Public History Steering Committee, 1982-96, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Public History Ad Hoc Student Group, 1982-83, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Internal Correspondence, 1991-94, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Internal Correspondence, 1995-99, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - External Correspondence, 1983-2002 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Memoranda to Students, 1982-84, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Subseries B: Course Files, 1981-2002
    - Program Histories, 1997-2002 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Curriculum Changes, 1982-96, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Curriculum Changes, 1997-01, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Professor Resumes, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Course Syllabi, 1982-2002 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Student Evaluations, 1982-89, 1982-1989 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - External Evaluations, 1992-99, 1992-1999 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Self-Evaluations, 1990-91, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Public History Program Website, 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Public History Program Website, 2001-2004, 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Public History Program Website, Mixed Media (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Adjunct Professors and Staff, 1982-96, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Research Associates, 1982-96, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Promotional Material (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Committee on a new Public History Program flyer, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Historical Archaeology Program, 1983-87, 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Series III: Publications, 1981-2002
  - Public History Newsletter, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1988-89, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1990-91, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1991-92, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1993-94, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1995-96: Planning and Resources, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Barcode: 3-1142-04227302-2
  - Public History Newsletter, 1995-96: Article Drafts and Issues, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1998-99: Planning and Resources, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Public History Newsletter, 1998-99: Article Drafts and Issues, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Public History Newsletter, 2000-02: Planning and Resources, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Public History Newsletter, 2000-02: Article Drafts and Issues, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Public History Newsletter, 2003-04, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Activities, 1981-2002
  - Subseries A: Public History Workshops, 1981-2002
    Some contents of this subseries contain personal information that may violate the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA).
    - Chelsea Workshop, 1982-83: Planning and Promotion, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Chelsea Workshop, 1982-83: Student Work, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Adoradio, Emery, "The Ironies of Community Self-Fulfillment in a Neighborhood Settlement House, 1895-1962.", April 26, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Chelsea Workshop, 1982-83: Reference Material, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Chelsea Workshop, 1982-83: Chelsea Historical Association Papers, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - East Village Workshop, 1985-86: Planning and Promotion, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - East Village Workshop, 1985-86: Student Work, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Elkins, Deborah and Susan Kozel, "In Search of Your Block's or Neighborhood's Past: Applications for Community Organizing.", January 27, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Miller, Melody, "From Bohemian to Beatnik: East Village Cafés.", January 15, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Scheuer, Kathlene, "Historic Architecture of the East Village.", January 15, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - East Village Workshop, 1985-86: Reference Material, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Planning, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Publicity, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Interviews, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Student Work, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Corey, Steven H., "A Neighborhood Through Time: Jones Street and Environs, 1930-1970.", May 15, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Dallett, Nancy, "Greenwich House.", January 26, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Hayes, Donald F., "The Greenwich House Board of Managers.", February 24, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Rosen, Miriam J. and Ragnhildur Vigfusdottir, "Greenwich Village Workshop: Greenwich House: The Shaping of a Community.", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Reference Material, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Reference Material, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Reference Material, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Barcode: 3-1142-04227303-0
    - Greenwich House Workshop, 1986-87: Later Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Washington Square Workshop, 1987-88: Planning and Promotion, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Washington Square Workshop, 1987-88: Student Work H-J, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Holmes, Sean P., "For the Betterment of Washington Square: The Washington Square Association, the Park, and the Rhetoric of Reform.", Spring 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Jones, Catherine, "Disease and Death: Their Effect on the Growing City.", March 3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Washington Square Workshop, 1987-88: Student Work O-Sch, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - O'Loughlin, Laura, "Juvenile Delinquency and Community Control: Washington Square Park, 1920-1950.", February 25, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Schiffman, Marlene, "Washington Square Park as Parade Ground.", January 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Washington Square Workshop, 1987-88: Student Work Sh, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Shaw, Aileen, "Washington Square Park and the Dynamics of Community Action, 1965-88.", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Washington Square Workshop, 1987-88: Exhibit, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - New York University Workshop, 1988-89: Planning and Promotion, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - New York University Workshop, 1988-89: Student Work Ben-Ber, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Bender, Pennee, "Greenwich Village / New York University Relations, 1947-1967.", December 19, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Berkley, Richard, "A Model Urban University: NYU's Land Use Politics, And Their Effect Upon The University's Identity, Rhetoric and Reality From 1885 to 1936.", Spring 1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Berkley, Richard, "Boom and Bust: N.Y.U.'s Land Use Policies, 1885-1936.", January 31, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Berkley, Richard, "New York University Between 1885 and 1936: An Expansive Plan for University Excellence.", Written 1988, amended October 23, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - New York University Workshop, 1988-89: Student Work De, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - DeMark, Susan, "Not One of Us: Discrimination and Protest Among Blacks at New York University in the 1920s.", Spring 1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - New York University Workshop, 1988-89: Student Work M-S, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Miller, Peter, "Violets on the Picket Line: Clerical Worker Unionism at N.Y.U. 1969-1988.", January 26, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Mart, Michelle, "McCarthyism at New York University, 1945-1954.", February 6, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)